Well,
hello.
I'm annoyed because I just recorded a whole
one of these and it didn't actually record.
So that's computers for you.
Sometimes I really think that they were a mistake.
So I'm going to be talking through a few
example chunks of code that I've written.
This is the first one which in HTML,
CSS and JavaScript is making this page and demonstrating
some of the things you can do with time media.
This would also work with an audio tag.
I'm using video tag today.
And the video tag that I'm using is pulling in
video that's hosted on the Internet Archive.
You can link directly to MP4 files that are hosted there,
which is really useful compared to somewhere
like YouTube where you need to embed their entire
player and use their entire code architecture,
which is easy to copy and paste but really difficult to customize.
So they want to keep their YouTube branding on things.
Having direct access to media files is key to
working with HTML5 or bringing video into P5.js.
And we can talk more about the constraints of that as well.
But looking through this,
we have some boilerplate HTML opener.
We have some CSS that is specifying that the width
of the video tag should be 80% of the viewport.
So this viewport window is squished to half
of my screen and the video is 80% of that.
It's also displayed none.
But yet we can see it.
How could that possibly be?
Images are also set to display none,
which means you shouldn't be able to see them.
And yet we see several of them.
They have a width set to 100 pixels, which is,
you know, seems about right.
Each of these pages.
The images are actually really large.
They're coming from a server
that I run.
This is from a document from the Senate Intel
Committee that I also just like to use for examples.
So here on our script,
you can see we have,
well,
in the HTML,
we have a paragraph tag here,
P tag with an ID that is empty.
We have a video tag
pointed at the racer trash remix of vapor Mario.
We have controls are on.
Otherwise, I wouldn't be able to hit play.
Or see the timeline.
And then in our JavaScript,
I have this video becomes a pointer to the DOM object of
the first video tag.
If I had multiple video tags,
I would target it probably by adding an ID to the video.
But since there's only one I can just
use video and quotes here with an ID,
there'd have to be a like a hash before it.
I have this counter here that was
just kind of for diagnostic purposes.
I was going to be able to see if I had a video tag.
I was writing this.
I have an async function here called go.
And I know async functions,
you're like,
wait,
what is this?
What's going on here?
So I'm making a function called go.
And you put the word async before the function.
And what that allows you to do is use this
keyword within the body of the function.
Oh, wait.
And await will wait
for something before it continues.
And.
There are a number of functions,
kind of native to JavaScript that return
promises rather than turning returning.
Like a DOM element or like this document query selector returns
a reference to the DOM element.
What wait for video does is actually
returns something called a promise.
So does load images.
And you can see that I did not put a wait before this.
And let's.
Let's see what that difference means.
So we have load images here.
And this is also an async function
because it is using await
in the body of the function.
And. What's going on in here is basically that I'm loading
15 images that have consecutive numbers in the file names.
So rather than pasting in 15 file names,
I'm using a for loop to kind of regenerate.
And. What is a pattern in the file name they all start with this text.
And they all finish with this text.
But in between are these three digit numbers.
That are like 00100200003. They actually start
with 0000. So it's like 000000014 is 15 images.
And I'm using.
I'm taking the eye the incrementing number here.
Turning it to a string and using this path.
And start method which all strings have access to.
And what pad start does is it takes a character in this case is zero.
And it makes sure that there are at least that many digits.
So three digits.
Or three characters.
So that this is kind of regenerating the 0000100002 counting up
and getting all the pages here.
When.
Then it does this wait for.
And then it sets its style display from none to in line,
which is why they're kind of floating next to each other here.
That's the default.
Display mode for images.
I believe video is
natively in line.
Also it may be in line block.
MDN would know.
So this wait for image function is,
as I said,
returning a promise.
And then I'm going to. And so I know it's like,
oh,
I see function so many times my brain starts to shove off.
And here's like a function here.
Wait for image.
And then a function here that doesn't have a name.
That is being passed from the promise.
And then a function here.
It's like, wait, what?
Huh? But if you bear with me,
this is returning a promise.
And the promise means that.
Only when it's resolved will this thing.
Actually happen.
And
what the order of events here is I'm adding this
event listener to the image tag so that when it loads,
it resolves.
And you know, if I really.
And then it will only fire once the video is doing a similar thing,
which you can see up here.
A function, a function, and a function.
The wait for video function.
Then.
It's returning the promise,
which also has a function inside that function is this event list
neuron video,
rather than load video has a lot of different.
Ready states.
And I'm using can play kind of video play.
Then that's good enough for me.
Once it can resolve,
it's possible based on different network conditions
that can play could actually fire multiple times.
So I'm also passing this preference object to say,
just do this once.
Otherwise, things could get confusing.
So we're waiting for video.
We're waiting for images going back to our function up here.
You notice that it's waiting for the
video before it changes it to visible.
It's not a waiting load images.
So let me see if if we can notice a difference between these.
You can see the images load really fast.
The video looks really fast.
Have a good network.
If I were to do a wait low images,
there might be a little bit slower.
Yeah.
So it loads.
It's not a good. It loads all the images and then it waits for the video
without this.
A wait load images runs.
Then it.
It immediately starts waiting for the video while they're loading.
So the presence of the await gives you a lot of
control over whether to wait for things or not.
Even though you know that multiple things are taking time.
And when you have a dependency around certain things.
This pattern of a wait,
a sink and promises gives you
a lot of control at the cost of some complage.
And promises have methods that let you like set
up things like a like promised out all will wait
for all of the like an array full of promises.
When all of these things are ready,
then you can go.
Or there's promised out race where you have a whole lot of promises.
And as soon as one of them is completed,
you're good.
And there conditions where like you might want to use those.
Now we have another event listener here.
As opposed to waiting for.
The video to have loaded and be able
to play or the image to have loaded.
This is time update and time update will fire.
Every time.
The playhead moves,
whether that's because the video is playing and the.
The numbers are going up right time is like because
the video is playing or like if I were to seek.
Like I just did even though it's paused.
Then time update still fires in that state.
Hey, it's not.
I'm just going to put it on the server.
So what's happening in this time update loop
is just some simple logic with if statements.
If the current time is greater than
10. And then this here refers to this.
The thing that you attach the event
listener to is can be referenced with this.
Could I also use
video.current time here.
Yes, because the scope of
the video that I set with a let.
Like I said, I'm going to use this.
Like would.
Carry down,
but sometimes it's more elegant to reference with this.
This current time is greater than
10. Then increase the playback rate.
Add. 0.05 to it.
This time update loop runs several times a second.
It's constantly looking.
Oh, is the time updated.
Yes, it has.
So this number should go up pretty quickly.
If it goes higher than six though,
it resets back to half speed,
which is slower than when it started.
And it starts.
It's going up again.
It also moves the play head back 40 seconds.
So it's like we're moving ahead.
We're speeding up.
And then we move backwards.
Maybe it's like two step backward.
Two steps forward.
One step back.
Kind of thing.
We're also reporting the playback rate into this div up here.
Or this.
It's actually a p tag.
Not a div.
And that's the entire contents of the code.
I'm going to reload it again.
The p disappears.
I hit play.
When we get to 10 seconds,
it should start going faster.
This is a preview for the Romeo and Juliet remix.
All right,
we get 10 playback rate starts going up.
There it goes.
When this number gets to six,
the current time should change.
So we're like we're over three.
For five.
Five times normal speed.
Now let's start looking at the timer.
We get to like.
Yeah,
it just went from like a minute 43 to a minute.
Oh, four.
So you can see how easy it is to change the location of the playhead.
Pause the video now.
And how you know,
you might be able to make a really simple structural film
with just these tools.
I'm going to give you some more.
But this is enough for for one file.
And thank you for listening to this.
And hopefully it actually recorded this time. If
it does, I'll do another one.
Okay.
Bye bye.